然而 尽管每个家庭都确实分到了房
However, although individual families were provided with a place of their own, once they moved in, they were stuck with what they got.
但一旦搬进去 他们就被卡死在这里了
这些公寓的所有者仍然是政府 而非住户
The government ultimately owned the apartments and not the families.
因此 你仍然得付租金
As such, you still had to pay rent.
但公平地说 租金其实相当低
But to be fair, It was pretty low.
通常是工资的4%到10%
Usually 4 to 10% of one's paycheck.
其实 谁分到什么房子还是由政府说了算的
Ultimately, it was the government's say who gets what,
而这还是取决于家庭成员在党内的地位和他们从事的工作
which again was dependent on the household members' standing in the party and what work they did.
搬到另一套公寓是一个复杂而繁琐的过程 常常需要好几年才能跑完手续
Moving to a different apartment was a complicated and tedious process that often took years.
如果你的当前住房中 每个家庭成员的生活空间少于5平方米
You could obtain an apartment of your own if within your current one each family member had less than 5 meters squared of living space,
或者有两个18岁以上的不是配偶的异性成员
there were two members of the opposite sex over 18, and weren't spouses, and were living in the same room.
而且还住在同一个房间的话 你就可以申请一套自己的公寓了
满足这些条件后 就可以申请搬迁
Upon meeting these conditions, one could apply for relocation.
但这并不一定意味着你真能有自己的住处
But this didn't mean necessarily getting your own place.
很多时候 申请人只会被分到一个合租公寓里的小房间
A lot of the time, a room within a communal apartment would be assigned to the applicant instead.
在苏联的欧洲“兄弟”们的城市里 从申请到获批需要10到15年
In cities in the European part of the Soviet Union, the time to realize an application would take between 10 to 15 years.
但即使你住在鸟不拉屎的地方 比如西伯利亚的一个小镇 那也得2到5年
But even if you were applying from a more rural area like a town in Siberia, it would take between 2 to 5.
也就是说 如果你从成年办理父母家（18岁）开始申请
Meaning that if you apply to move out from your parents, When you just turned 18,
那你可能得等到30来岁才能分到房
you would only be able to do so once you were well into your 30s.
新婚夫妇则可以通过和刚离婚的人交换住处来绕过这个系统
Newlywed couples bypassed this system by exchanging their living arrangements with new divorcees,
with a small under the table exchange, of course.
当然 人情世故啥的肯定还是得有
有些住房则直接来自工厂
Some housing came directly from industrial plants.
例如 如果你在钢铁厂找到工作 公司会提供公寓
For example, if you got a job at a steel mill, the company would provide you with an apartment, but losing the job meant losing the home.
但这意味着你丢了工作 房子也得跟着一起没
一些行业还提供宿舍
Some industries also offered dormitories.
那里的工人们通常与2到4个人同住一个房间
Where workers shared rooms with 2 to 4 people.
这使得每个宿舍楼层能容纳40到100个工人 厨房和厕所则是共享的
Each dormitory floor could house 40 to 100 workers, with shared kitchens and bathrooms.
私人住房也是有的 农村和郊区尤其多 因为那里的政府管得不多
Private housing existed too, especially in rural areas and small towns where the government had little involvement.
很多家庭都有自己的房子 而且在政府批准下 自己盖房子也是可以的
Families often kept their own homes, and it was possible to build one yourself with government approval.
但是 所有建筑费用都得自己掏腰包 而且活儿大多还得自己干
However, all construction costs had to be covered personally, and much of the labor was usually done by the homeowners themselves.
自己有房子的人 还可以把房间租给别人
Those who own their own homes were also allowed to rent out rooms to tenants.
搬到别的城市也不是件容易事
Moving cities was a complicated process.
比如 你想从莫斯科搬到... 乌尔库茨克吧 你得先在那儿找到工作
If you wish to move from, say, Moscow to I don't know, let's say Urkutsk, you needed to first get a job there.
可是 要找工作 你得先有当地的居住证 这得有房子才行
But to get a job, you would need a residency permit by having an apartment there.
但反过来 没有工作你也弄不到房子
But again, you couldn't get an apartment without a job.
说白了 这就是个康米版二十二条军规
Essentially a communist catch 22 situation.
所以 想搬家的人通常会从私人房东（地主）那里租房
So those who wish to move to a new place would often rent out a room from a private landlord.
这很搞笑 因为康米要打的不就是地主吗
Which is um a bit ironic considering landlords were considered the ultimate evil by communists.
最后 还有一种办法是通过合作社买自己的公寓
Lastly, there was also an option of purchasing your own apartment via a cooperative.
你可以向合作社贷款来买自己的公寓
You could take out a loan from the cooperative and purchase your own apartment.
首付大约是总价的5%到30%
The down payment would range between 5 to 30% of your total cost.
剩下的钱则要分几年按月还 政府还会给点补贴
The rest was to be paid out over several years and monthly rates, which to an extent were subsidized by the government.
不过 因为费用太高 只有苏联的精英阶层才能选这个
But due to the high costs, this only remained an option to Soviet elites.
当然 那些在合作社有人 能跳过那长得要命的排队的人除外
And those with connections in the cooperatives who could bypass the incredibly long queues.
住房政策随着勃列日涅夫的上台再次改变了
The housing policy was changed again with the arrival of Brezhnev.
60年代中期到80年代 16层以上的老破大（其实里面还是小）是主流
Between the mid-60s up until the 80s, giant 16-story plus commie blocks came into existence.
它们有不同的建筑色调、不那么单调的外墙、不同的几何形状之类的
Their design was experimented with different shades of color, less bland facades, different geometric shapes.
还有更好的保温措施 还解决了让建筑闻起来像卷心菜的问题
Better insulation and alternatives to smelling like cabbage were implemented.
最重要的是 它们有电梯 而前几代的老破小是真没有的
And most importantly, they had elevators, which previous generations of commie blocks did not.
这里要画重点
This was a crucial development as many old folks struggled with leaving their apartments due to having to climb up and down several stories.
因为许多老人都由于必须爬楼而根本离开不了家
总的来说 这些建筑发展都恰逢东欧集团经济趋于稳定的时期
All in all, these developments coincided with the stabilization of the Eastern Blocks' economic situation.
当时还涌现了一大批极具代表性、造型古怪的粗野主义建筑
Most iconic and weird looking Brutalist buildings were constructed in this time period.
毕竟 跟黑道复制人似的灰色老破小是不能算地表的啊喂
In an effort to give the city some actual landmarks instead of just a sea of copy-pasted gray blocks.
但是 这些看起来很酷的建筑中的大多数公寓都提供给了精英和那些有关系的人
But again, most of the apartments in these cool looking buildings were provided to elites and those with nepottic connections.
其实 这是苏式楼房的一个本质问题
And ultimately, this was a big problem with commie blocks.
作为一个声称要提供无阶级社会的政权
For a regime that claimed it was here to provide a classless society,
corruption and nepotism were the decisive factor in one's living arrangements.
决定一个人住房的关键因素却是腐败和裙带关系
在某些情况下 甚至种族也是考量标准之一
And in some cases, ethnicity was too.
如果你是工人阶级的一员 你就只能生活在像沙丁鱼罐头一样狭小的地方里
If you were a member of the working class, you were forced to live in sardine like conditions.
而那些赫鲁晓夫打了个喷嚏也要鼓掌的人则拿到了私人庄园
While someone who cheered Khrushchev's every sneeze like it was a standing ovation was rewarded with a private estate.
其次 许多历史城市如布加勒斯特、诺维萨德和华沙
Secondly, a lot of historic cities like Bucharest, Novisad, and Warsaw
都有大块大块的充满了美丽的历史建筑的地区
had entire segments filled with beautiful historic buildings that spend centuries
但这些建筑都被拆除了 变成了缺乏灵魂和个性、丑陋的灰色单调建筑
demolished and replaced with ugly gray monotone blocks devoid of soul and personality.
对此最好的写照是布加勒斯特的人民宫
This can be best seen with the building of the People's Palace in Bucharest.
那片为该市赢得“东方巴黎”美名的老城区大部分都被夷为平地
Most of the old town for which the city got the name Paris of the East was leveled to the ground to erect this monstrosity.
而在通往它的统一大道两旁
On the Unity Boulevard that leads up to it,
还盖起了许多豪华的住宅楼 专门给罗马尼亚的最高层政府官员居住
numerous extravagant commie blocks were erected, which housed the highest government elites of Romania.
再考虑到康米意识形态的基础是平等和摧毁阶级结构 这简直令人作呕
Which is disgusting considering the whole basis of socialist and communist ideology was equality and the demolishing of class structure.
旧日资产阶级的图腾被悉数砸碎 取而代之的却是新权贵的徽章
But symbols of the bourgeoisie were destroyed only to be replaced with symbols of the new society's bourgeoisie.
那反对的也有说法的啊
A defense for commie blocks is that many of these historic buildings and most housing in general was destroyed during the second world war.
许多这些历史建筑和大多数住房在二战期间被摧毁了不是吗
这倒是真的
And that is true.
战后 整个欧洲的人们确实都需要住房 而且都很急
After the war, people across Europe needed housing, and they needed it fast.
而这些建筑原本也确实是为了解决这个问题而设计的 也确实有点用
And these blocks were meant to be a solution for this problem, which they definitely did help with.
可以说 它们处理这个问题的方式比西欧的替代方案更好
Arguably, they tackled the issue better than alternatives in Western Europe.
然而 这些所谓康米风格建筑原本只是用来给还不能自立国家的临时解决方案
However, commie blocks were originally envisioned as a temporary solution until the countries could stand up on their feet,
但最终却成了永远存在的老破小
but ended up as a permanent one instead.
战后 西欧的大部分地区也经历了严重的住房危机
Much of Western Europe was also undergoing a severe housing crisis after the war.
无论是英国、德国还是苏联 大家都无家可归
Homelessness was a major issue in countries like the UK, Germany, and the Soviet Union.
尽管苏联确实通过建造这些“康米建筑”部分解决了这个问题
And although the USSR did make a monumental step with the building of commie blocks to solve this problem.
但西欧国家也是如此 他们也大量投资于社会住房和住房补贴
So did Western European states, who also invested heavily into social housing and housing subsidies.
英国制造的预制房屋是最好的例子
Prefabs made by the UK are the best example.
与苏联的做法类似
Similar to what the Soviets were doing,
英国也建造了数十万套廉价制造的临时公寓和新城镇 来安置战争难民
the British erected hundreds of thousands of cheaply made temporary apartments and new towns to house refugees from the war.
但随着国家的经济逐渐转好 它们被更好的永久性住房取代了
But as the country strengthened economically, they were replaced with better permanent homes.
然而 无家可归问题在欧洲西部仍然持续了一段时间
However, homelessness did prevail as an issue in the west of the continent for some time after.
但东欧集团也是如此
But this was the case in the Eastern Bloc as well.
一个常见的误解是 苏联通过建造共产主义风格建筑完全消除了无家可归问题
A common misconception is that the Soviet Union eradicated homelessness with the construction of counter blocks.
事实并非如此
This isn't the case.
苏联官方否认无家可归问题的存在 并将其列为犯罪
Officially, the USSR denied the existence of homelessness as a whole and listed it as a crime,
because its existence would undermine the claim that socialism guarantees basic needs.
因为这会消除苏联“要啥有啥”的制度优越性
但战后几年里 它仍然存在 因为公寓的生产总是无法满足需求
But following the years after the war, it persisted as production of apartments could not reach demand.
但没有居住证的人会被逮捕或判处强迫劳动
People without a residency permit would be arrested or sentenced to forced labor.
从劳动营出来的前罪犯 释放后常常没地方去
Ex-convicts from work camps often didn't have anywhere to go after their release.
而那些想搬到另一个城市的人 由于难以获得居住证
And those who wished to move to another city had to come up with
只能自谋出路 比如睡在地下室和火车站
creative solutions due to the difficulties of obtaining a residency permit like sleeping in basements and train stations.
最后 还有孤儿的问题
Lastly, there was the issue of orphans.
许多在战争中失去父母或被父母遗弃的孩子 比如罗马尼亚的 都陷入了无家可归的境地
Many kids who lost their parents during the war or were abandoned by them, as was the case in socialist Romania, were homeless.
国家会把他们安置在拥挤的孤儿院中（其实跑的不少）
The state would place them in overcrowded orphanages from which many escaped, send them to labor colonies and special schools.
又或是把他们送到劳动营和特殊学校
确实 在苏联 无家可归被视为犯罪
It is true that homelessness was treated as a crime in the USSR, but it was treated the same way as addiction is treated in the United States.
但政府处理这些行为的方式... 只能说跟美国处理吸毒一样
总之 康米建筑在当时只能说是必要之恶
All in all, commie blocks were a necessary evil at the time.
它们确实为那些因战争流离失所的人提供了救济 并帮助缓解了普遍的住房危机
They did provide a lot of relief to those displaced by the war and helped with the general housing crisis.
然而 对它们的管理非常差 助长了腐败和裙带关系
However, they were severely mismanaged, promoted corruption and nepotism,
and destroyed cultural heritage and limited liberty of movement and class mobility.
还破坏了文化遗产 也限制了行动自由和阶级流动性
因此 最重要的是要意识到它们为什么坏和东欧人不喜欢它们是有理由的
As such, it is important to be aware of their dark past and negative symbol they present to many in Eastern Europe.